Well, good afternoon and welcome to the
June 1st meeting of the public services
committee. Um, if you are here with us
in person, if you will make sure that
your cell phone is turned to silent, we
would appreciate it. When you approach
the podium, if you'll make sure that the
green light is on and that um you um
make sure you give us your name, we
would appreciate that as well. If you're
joining us from online and would like to
make a comment under public comment, um
please use the raised hand function. And
with that, first item
number seven, ordinance third reading,
amending section 13.20.050,
general prohibitions and section
13.20.070
local limits of chapter 13.20 20
wastewater treatment and disposal of the
code of the city of Cheyenne, Wyoming to
revise local discharge limits and
related provisions in compliance with ND
NPDES and WPDEES
permit requirements.
>> Do we have a staff report today?
>> Matt, you can go ahead.
>> Can you guys hear me? All right.
>> We can.
>> Excellent. So, Madam Chair, through you,
Matt Belo, Cheyenne, Wyoming, Board of
Public Utilities, Water Recre Division
Manager. I just spoke with Mr. Al Garcia
with EPA this morning. Um, he stated to
me that he did not receive any public
comment during the 30-day public
notification process. He will be issuing
the BOP a letter um this Friday stating
that they did not receive any comments
and we can proceed further. So, with
that, I would motion to uh proceed with
third and final reading next week and
I'd be happy to answer any questions.
Hey, are there any um questions from the
dis for the staff?
>> Okay, thank you Mr. Bo.
>> Thank you.
>> Um any public comment?
>> Okay, I would entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman,
>> yes, Councilman Renie,
>> I move to approve on third reading.
>> Second. We have a motion to approve on
third and final reading and a second
from Dr. Emmens. Um any discussion?
Hearing none. All in favor say I.
>> I opposed.
>> Okay. This item will move forward with a
recommendation um to approve at the next
council meeting. Next item, please.
Number 10, ordinance third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located
southwest of the intersection of HR
Ranch Road and Judy Lee Drive and
southeast of HR Ranch Road and Judy Lee
Drive from JL Ranch PUD planned unit
development to NR2 neighborhood
residential medium density.
>> Great. The staff report, Miss Dennis,
>> Morgan Dennis, Planning and Development.
Um, there have been no changes to the
staff report and staff has not received
any further public comment and I stand
for questions. Is there anyone on the
dis have any questions from Morgan?
>> Okay. Uh, public comment.
>> Good afternoon, Mr. Swain.
>> Uh, good afternoon, Madam Chair. Uh,
members of the public service committee.
Just reiterating what um Morgan said and
then one elaboration. This isn't
changing any density, keeping density
exactly the same. Um, the development is
also going to be consistent with
pre-existing patterns. This is just a
nuance to allow relief and landscaping
requirements, which will allow a more
affordable system development fee with
the board of public utilities.
>> Okay. Are there any questions?
Okay. Thank you, Brandon.
>> Any other public comment?
Okay. And hearing none, I would
entertain a motion.
Madame Chair, um I move
>> totally lost my train of thought. I move
to approve.
>> Second.
>> Okay, we have a motion from Dr. Amens
and a second from Dr. Renie. Is there
any discussion?
Hearing none. All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed?
>> Okay. Next item, please. Number 12,
ordinance third reading, amending the
official zoning map of the city of
Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located in
Cheyenne Business Park and Camp Stool
Business Park in Eastern Cheyenne along
I80 from LI Light Industrial, HIV
Industrial, and CB Community Business to
BP Business Park. Staff report, please.
>> Madam Chair, members of Committee,
Conor, Planning Development Department.
Just wanted to throw up a map that kind
of shows the area just so everybody's
aware where it is. Um,
this is on third reading. Again, this is
a zone change basically for two business
parks out here that are already zoned
LIHI and a little bit of community
business proposing to be reszoned to BP
Business Park. Um,
you should all have a substitute in
front of you. Um, there were two
property owners that had actually
contacted us and would like to be
excluded from the zone change. So, we
are requesting they be excluded and they
are um excluded within the substitute
that's in front of you. Um their
reasonings it goes back to the same as
the original person who requests to be
out. They'd like to just have their
flexibility of being allowed outdoor
storage within their existing zone
districts. So, one of the properties
will stay heavy industrial and the other
one would stay light industrial.
That's already what they are out there.
Um, and staff has no issues with that.
If they want to become part of the
business park zone district in the
future, they can always apply for that
and come back before council and request
that change. Um, otherwise, there's no
other proposed changes besides that
substitute. I am available for any
questions.
>> Thank you, Connor. Any questions for
staff?
>> Okay. Any public comment?
Hey, seeing none or hearing none, I
would entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chair, I would move to approve.
>> Second.
>> Madam Chairman.
>> Yes. Chairwoman,
>> I move to amend by substitute.
Substitute is dated today, I believe.
>> June 1st.
>> June 1st, 2026.
>> Second. Hey, we have an amendment to uh
substitute
by with the substitution provided on
June 1st. Um is there any we'll go back
out I guess for public comment. Any
public comment on the substitute
amendment?
Okay. Um any comments from the dis?
Okay.
Hearing none and seeing none, all in
favor of the amendment to substitute uh
dated June 1st say I.
>> I opposed. Same sign. Okay. We now have
the amendment. And so now we can vote on
the main motion. So um any discussion?
>> No ma'am.
>> Okay. I would entertain a motion.
>> I have one.
>> I already made
>> Oh, I'm sorry. We have a motion made by
Dr. Emman, seconded by Dr. Renie. Um all
in favor say I.
>> I. I
>> opposed. Okay. This item will move
forward with a recommendation uh to
approve on third and final reading. Next
item number 16 ordinance second reading
amending section 1.4.3
and 5.8.8 of the unified development
code and creating section 5.8.9
carports to create definitions and
standards for carports.
>> Okay. Is there a staff report?
Madam chair, members of the committee,
Conway Planning and Development
Department,
the text amendment before you um
proposes changes to the unified
development code to basically create
carport regulations.
Um right now carports are considered
accessory buildings um in the UDC.
So what that means is when we review
carports um accessory buildings have
required setbacks already. They have
required sizes. is you're only permitted
two accessory buildings per lot.
Um the biggest thing is with accessory
buildings, they're not allowed in your
front yard. They need to be 10 ft behind
the front of your house, which basically
any carport that's on a front driveway
right now throughout the city is a
zoning violation, is illegal. Um,
same thing if you have a corner lot and
you have your side uh side street.
Basically, if you have a carport on a
side driveway there, you need to be 25
ft from that side property line, which
in most cases they're not.
So, with this, and I will say staff gets
dozens of calls on carports. Um, I can
probably say since starting this text
amendment, I've had over 20 calls about
carports. Um, majority of them would
like to have a carport on their front
driveway. Um,
so with this text amendment, it does
look at creating specific standards for
carports um, and would actually allow
them to be on people's front driveways.
So with this change um
it basically removes carports from being
reviewed as accessory buildings. So they
become basically their own thing within
the UDC. Um you can basically still have
your two accessory buildings and then
you can have a carport. Uh so the way
that staff proposes it is that um you
still have to have a house. You can't
just put a a carport on a vacant
property. Same thing with accessory
buildings. Accessory buildings you can't
just have a garage on a vacant property.
You have to have a house. Um and then
uh with the proposal, planning
commission did make some changes. So
those are in the memo. Um but with with
what is proposed, it basically allows
the uh the front yard basically front
yard carports only need to be set back a
minimum of 5t from a sidewalk and 10
feet from the curb.
Even with those setbacks, um depending
on where the property line sits, the
carport still has to be on the property.
It's never allowed in the rightway. So
depending on where that property line
sits, if it is the back of the sidewalk,
you still got to be 5t off the sidewalk.
If the property line is 10t off the back
of the sidewalk, well then you got to be
10t. Um you still have to be on your
property.
Same thing with corner lots. So, if
somebody has a corner lot and they have
a side basically access to the side
street, they would be uh required to
have a uh the setback of uh 10 feet from
the curb and then 5 ft from the
sidewalk.
With carports, we are limiting them to
one per dwelling unit. So, if you got a
single family home, you can have one
carport. We do put um kind of relief in
here. So, if somebody does want another
carport, they can go to the board of
adjustment. Um it's not a flatout you
can only have the one. There is the
option to go through the conditional use
process, go see if you can get approval
for another um another carport.
Uh we limit the size to 600 square ft
question.
>> And then again, if you want to exceed
the 600 ft, you go to the board of
adjustment. same thing uh conditional
usewise.
And then one of the other regulations we
put in here is that a carport um
basically shall not have no more than uh
two sides of the carport uh may be
enclosed in any manner on any side where
enclosure is provided. The lower 50% of
the vertical wall uh facade shall remain
open. Basically, this basically it
prevents carports from having those
walls that go straight to the ground and
where they become tunnels and then they
become just storage for junk and other
things besides a car. Um,
so that's what G basically does is limit
how enclosed they can be.
And then
um basically with any carport, this is
already something that's required, but
we put it in here as well as any
basically building permits are required
for carports.
Um so we just have that standard in here
that with a carport, you're going to
need a building permit.
So those are really the big changes. Um,
the major change with this is basically
taking carports out of being considered
accessory buildings and allowing them to
be on people's front driveways. Um,
again, staff gets calls and questions
and usually people not very happy with
me when I tell them they can't have a
carport in their front driveway. Um, but
that is something that we hear on a
regular basis. Um, a lot of it usually
happens after we have a major hail
storm, um, or major weather events, but
even this year, like I said, I've had
dozens of phone calls. Um, and actually,
I've told most people, well, do have a
text amendment. It is going to council.
Um, if you do want to show up to council
and support it, please feel free to. Um,
but right now, under current code, I
would not be able to permit your carport
on your front driveway. It' have to be
10 ft behind the front of the house. uh
you do need to be three feet from the
house otherwise it becomes part of the
house uh due to our accessory building
regulations. So it's basically you need
to put it in the backyard um in most
cases.
Planning commission did hear this item.
Um they did make some modifications that
I had gone over um just with the
definition to carports and then also the
distance being changed instead of being
to the property line. They proposed
changing it to being the five feet from
any public sidewalk and then 10 feet
from the curb. Um staff's original
proposal was two feet from basically the
property line. Uh planning commission
felt that they wanted it to be from
sidewalk and from uh the curb.
Other than that, staff does recommend
approval of this. Planning commission
did recommend approval with those
modifications which are uh within the
ordinance before you. So there doesn't
have to be any changes made by council
at the moment unless you propose any
changes. Uh and with that I stand for
any questions
madam chairwoman.
>> Yes sir.
>> Through you to Mr. White. So the only um
restriction on size and perhaps I've
missed it is the 600 square feet. So I
mean that means one could be 10T by 60
foot. There's no restriction on length.
Is that correct Mr. Chair through you?
That is correct. They they do need to
meet other setback requirements. So you
still need to meet your required side
setback for the parcel and things like
that. But if they can somehow fit a
10x60 on their property, they can
already do that under accessory building
regulations. Technically, um I don't
foresee many people being able to fit a
10x60 on their front driveway. Uh most
houses only sit 25 ft from their front
property line as is. So
you won't see a 10x60 on a front
driveway, but yes, they technically
could put a 10 x60 in their backyard if
their backyard is big enough. But they
can already do that under current code
as well.
>> Yeah, for the backyard. I just that'd
have to have a really long driveway. Um,
and then the other question I had was in
reference to height. And I understand
that a carport shouldn't be
any shouldn't be taller than the than
the home or the residence, but there's a
provision in there that you could
actually
change that or wave that restriction
administratively.
Can you imagine a situation where a
carport would be
taller than you would approve a carport
that would be taller than the residence.
>> Mr. Truth for you, I don't foresee most
people wanting carports to tall taller
than the house. Um, they don't make
twotory ones with a ramp, right?
>> Not that I'm aware of. Um, the only time
I would potentially foresee something
like that is if somebody wanted a
carport for their RV. Um, depending on
the height of that, even that still may
not be taller than the house. I'm trying
to picture one of those. I haven't seen
one of those. Most people just build a
garage at that point. Um, but that would
be the only time I would foresee there
being a carport that's possibly taller
than the house is maybe if it's for an
RV because I believe most carports have
standard when you go to buy it at
Samards or Lowe's or wherever you can
buy them. I believe they have standards
for them already and a majority of the
ones I see are not taller than the
house.
>> Okay. Thank you, Madam Chairwoman.
>> Any other questions from the DAS? Dr.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Um, can you
tell me why this why we why did we
originally have this requirement?
>> Restriction. Yeah.
>> So, restriction on having them in the
front.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. So, Madam Chair, through you. So,
the UDC isn't it's not specific on what
carports are right now. So, the way that
staff has always reviewed them as
they're accessory buildings. Um, they
need building permits. They are it's
like a shed. A shed's considered an
accessory building. So, we've always
reviewed them as accessory buildings.
And the accessory building code with the
way it's currently written, accessory
buildings have required front setbacks,
which are you got to be 10t behind the
front of the house. you can't have them
in the front yard. So, you can't have a
shed in the front yard. You can't build
a detached garage in your front yard.
Um,
so that's how we reviewed carports. And
because we lumped them into accessory
buildings,
that's where they fell. They have to be
10 ft behind the front of the house and
they can't be in the front of us.
>> Follow up, please. So, I guess what I'm
trying to get at is why do we want to
maybe I should go this way. Why do we
want to get rid of this requirement? So,
Madam Chair, through you, um, we were
approached by a council member to look
into this and then, as I mentioned, we
get calls from citizens all the time.
Um, I know you weren't on council at the
time, but I think it was a few years
ago, I actually did a work session in
front of council about carports, um, and
was trying to take a feeler on does
council want us to look in making some
changes. And at the time, I was actually
proposing that any carport in the front
yard would actually have to have design
standards. So, they'd have to be similar
looking to the house. They can't just be
the metal carports. Um, we were
basically requested not to have the
design standards when we brought this
forward. Um, and basically the other
thing is to just look at allowing them
in the front yard. Um, again, we get so
many calls about this. Um,
it's a constant question for what people
want. So that's that's why we've brought
it forward is just from citizens kind of
commenting a ton at wanting these and
then a council member asking us to
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Thank you Madam Chairwoman again through
through you to Mr. White. So your last
statement brought up a question. I just
always made the assumption that these
would have to be aligned with the
driveway, but you said they could be in
the front. You just said they could be
in the front yard. So, and they plop one
on the grass in front of their house,
>> madam chair, through you. So, actually,
I believe we do actually have it in this
section where they have to follow
driveway standards and will have to be
on the driveway.
>> This is I know I stated they can be in
the front yard, but how I'm looking at
it is when most people are requesting
these, they want it on their front
driveway.
>> It's in the front.
>> Yeah, it's basically on the front
driveway. It's not in their front yard
next to the driveway. It's usually I
have a driveway. I want to put a
cardboard on it.
Thank you, Madam Chairman.
>> Councilman Labor.
>> Thank you, Madam Chair. Um, so this is
something that I'm seeing more and more
uh in my neighborhood and something that
is uh
a concern. I I understand the placement
of the carport on Oops.
Yes, ma'am. Am I okay now? All right.
Uh so um
what I've just heard is that
this
ordinance would establish that use on
the driveway and not in the yard. Is
that correct,
>> Mr. Chair? That is correct.
>> And so how do we define the driveway?
Sorry, give me one second. I'm trying to
find that section that we had added
because I know we had discussed within
our department and then I believe we
added something that specifies that they
have to meet the driveway standards of
the UDC.
Oh yes, there it is. So carport shall
meet all standards for driveways within
the zone district. So our driveway
standards are under article 4. They
basically specify how wide your driveway
can be that it has to be set back from
property lines, things of that nature.
So by having to meet the driveway
standards, you're basically limiting the
carport to the driveway. Thank you.
Any
other questions for staff?
Okay.
Uh we'll go ahead and
>> Sorry, one more thing, Madam Chair.
>> There is a substitute on this one. Um I
forgot to mention the substitute is
basically just adding an extra um
section to the ordinance that uh
basically adds the new section 5.8.9
to the beginning of 5.8 in the list of
subsections so that it's within that
table of contents. So, that's the only
thing the substitute does. It doesn't
change any additional language. It's
just something that I forgot to put in
the original ordinance um to help with
amending the UDC.
>> Thank you.
>> Hey, um any public comment?
Madame Chair, members of public service
committee, Mark Moody, China City
Council WI 3. Uh, Mr. W spoke it
perfectly. I also do support what the
plan commission did. What I gave to you
guys in front of you are the setbacks.
The first page is the 10- foot. Okay.
measure myself with a tape measure. And
then the second one is the five foot
from the sidewalk. And again,
public wanting this and you can see it
pretty clearly. So this is really just
to give you more of a visual image of
it. Okay, I think that's very
reasonable. And again, it has to be
there with the driveway. You can't just
plop it there in the front yard as we
said. And also too, again, it has those
requirements. So it can't be defined as
a garage. And like I said, I did work
with planning department there to make
sure all these nuances were there. So I
definitely would urge to support this.
One other thing to look at too from an
affordable housing perspective. Let's
say a builder wants to come in not put a
garage in just allow for the carports
be a way to cut down on cost. So I'll
stand for questions.
>> Any questions for Mr. Moody? Thank you.
Council, thank you.
>> Good afternoon.
If you'll just push that green button
and uh tell us your name, that'd be
great. Thank you. You may have to pull
that mic down towards you.
>> Yeah.
>> To the floor. Me, too.
>> My name is K. Sheen, and I have no
investment in this. I'm just listening.
Um, but it seems to me that only five
feet from the sidewalk seems pretty
close to the fi sidewalk. And for people
walking along the sidewalk or bringing
their dogs or whatever with them or just
visually, it seems awfully close to the
sidewalk to me. Uh, and wondered if it
could be possibly pushed further back
into their yards, their property.
That's just a comment I have. It just
sounds awfully close to the sidewalk.
And visually, if there's no consistency
with the carports themselves in terms of
how they look, um, who knows what would
be there.
>> Yeah,
>> that's just a comment.
>> Great. Thank you for your comments.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah.
>> Any other public comment?
Okay. I would um seeing none or hearing
no further public comment, I would
entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairman, I'd move to approve on
second reading.
>> Second. We have a motion from Dr. Renie
and a second from Dr. Emmens. Um
any discussion? Okay,
>> Madam Chairwoman.
>> Okay, Dr. Ren,
>> in reading this, I just read a sentence
that I missed before, so perhaps Mr.
White might have to address this or the
sponsor, but under UDC 1.4.3
defined terms, it says the structure may
be freestanding or attached to another
structure. So, we were already told it
can't has to be 3 ft away from the house
or it's considered an addition.
So, what is an example of another
structure it could be attached to?
Madam chair through you. So with the way
that we have the definition again,
carports are no longer considered
accessory buildings. So that 3-foot rule
doesn't apply.
So it would allow you to attach a
carport to the front of the house and
have that extend out, which I actually
did have somebody who would like to do
so, but they're actually not doing a
metal one. They'd actually like to build
off the front of the house and come out.
>> Got it. Um, same thing. You technically
could attach a carport to the side of a
detached garage or you can attach in
some fashion.
Most of the times building apartment
prefers that you don't attach the
carport to your house physically. Um,
especially if it's one of the metal
ones, but
that's just the definition we have is
that they can be freestanding or
attached.
>> Okay. Thank you, Madam Chairman. That
answered my question. Any other
questions or any other com comments on
the dis
>> madam chairwoman?
>> Yes, Dr. Winnie
>> under 5.8.9 carports C and one and
three. I do not I tend to agree with
Miss Sheen that just spoke and said that
5T was too close. This actually allows
the director
um to administratively adjust that to
zero feet. I do not like that. So,
Madame Chairwoman, I would make a motion
to amend by deleting both sentences
where it says the director may reduce
the setback to zero feet. Um, in both C1
and C3
and C3 is a little longer, but I don't I
think if we remove that zero line
setback,
um, neither sentences
needed.
>> Okay, we have a motion from Dr. Rene to
eliminate uh C1 uh the portion that says
the director may reduce the setback to 0
feet through administrative adjustment
upon finding that the carport will not
interfere with a current or future
public sidewalk. And also on C3, the
director may reduce the setback to 0
feet through administrative adjustment
upon finding that the carport will not
interfere with a current or future
public sidewalk. Uh setback reduction
only applies where the carport opening
directly faces and takes access from the
adjacent street
>> etc. etc.
>> It's continues going and we have a
second. Is there any discussion on the
amendment?
>> Oh, I'm sorry. Let's go out for public
comment. Any public comment on the
amendment?
>> Okay. Um, yes,
>> Madam Chairwoman, I do have a question
for somebody. Um, is there anything that
contradicts that elsewhere in the UDC?
Madam chair through you. No, there's
nowhere else in the UDC that would
contradict that. Basically, we had that
in there um
when it was originally proposed to
planning commission as being 2 feet from
the property line and it would allow the
director to reduce it to zero to the
property line. I can see where now that
it has changed to five feet from the
sidewalk, 10 feet from the curb, it
still it doesn't say to the property
line, just is down to zero feet. So
with the changes, if if city council is
good with the changes planning
commission made, then this would
probably make sense to delete.
>> Any other comments from the dis?
>> Madam Chairman,
>> yes,
>> I obviously my rational I explained my
rationale when I made made the
amendment. I just I think a zero foot
setback from the sidewalk is
too close. Yes,
>> it looks like we have a comment from Mr.
Brody.
>> Madame Chairman, John Brody, city
attorney. Uh, I would just note that the
substitute has a conforming amendment
that's required regardless of which way
the council goes. Um, so if you're going
to further amend the substance of the
proposal, um, I would, uh, I guess
request that you move the substitute
first and then amend from there. But
obviously we can we can address it
however you'd like. Okay.
>> A little late for that.
Okay.
Okay. So, um
we we have the option to kill this
amendment and then re bring it back.
Okay.
>> That's probably the best solution is
vote it down and then redo it.
>> Okay. So, um
any other discussion hearing? None. Um
all in favor of the amendment say I.
>> All opposed.
>> No.
>> Okay. the uh that amendment dies for
lack of a of um a vote. So
now we're on the substitute. We need a
substitute introduced or amended.
>> Got it.
>> No, go ahead.
>> Madam Chair, when I move to amend by
substitute dated again June 1st,
>> actually I think it's uh May 20th.
>> What is it?
>> Or 28th, I'm sorry.
>> Yeah, May 28th.
>> In front of me.
So, thank you for the correction dated
May 28th, 2026. Okay. Second. Okay. We
have a motion to amend by substitution
dated May 28th and a second by Dr.
Emmens. Um any um it will go out for
public comment on the substitution.
Okay. Hearing none or seeing none. Um
any discussion from the committee?
All in favor of uh substituting by
amendment dated May 28th say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed.
>> Okay.
>> Madam chairwoman.
>> Yes. Dr. Renie.
>> I would like to move move to amend um in
UDC 5.8.9 carports under C1 and three to
delete the reference to the director may
reduce this setback to zero feet through
administrative adjustment
etc.
Okay. Second. Okay. We have a motion um
and from Dr. Renie and a second from Dr.
Emmens to amend uh the the portion of
the UDC 5.8.9 under carports C1 and C3
that it starts with the director may
reduce the setback um etc. Is there are
there any public comments?
Uh Mark, shine city council 3. Madam
chair, I'm okay with this. So just like
I said, still five feet is more than
enough. Thank you.
Any other public comment, Jennifer? I
don't see any. Okay.
Okay. Any um discussion by the committee
hearing? None. I would entertain a
motion. We have one. Oh,
>> we have a motion. So all in favor say I.
I. opposed.
Okay. So, now we have an amended
substitute. Now, we need to actually
vote on the actual motion, I believe.
>> So, yeah, I know it's a lot of voting on
it. You're right.
>> So, um all in favor of the original
motion that's been substituted and
amended now
>> say I.
>> I.
>> Oppose.
>> Okay. That motion that item will move
forward to the uh full council at the
next meeting of the council. Next item,
please. Number 17, ordinance, second
reading, amending section 1.3.11,
nonconformities,
1.4.4,
definitions, 1.4.5,
interpretation of zoning map, 2.2.7,
special use approval, 5.1.2,
zoning districts established, and 5.1.4
use table and creating 5.6.10 10
regional entertainment re overlay
district and 5.7.13
gaming center development standards and
setting an effective date for
compliance.
Okay. Staff report.
>> First of all, can I have sharing
privileges real quick on Zoom?
Chair, members of the committee, Charles
Bloom, planning and development
director. I'm going to get promoted real
quick to a panelist. I'll walk through
this. um very efficiently. Um I do want
to note that there are two changes that
we will be bringing forward at the next
committee meeting. I just wanted to
double check those with you all first
before we move forward. I will let you
know those as we walk through this
presentation.
Per, this is a a quick overview of
regulations that we are looking to
create that will actually regulate the
historic horse racing activities a
little bit differently in the community.
Right now, they are conditional uses in
a variety of our districts in our
community business district, our
mixeduse business district, and a few
others. That requires that the board of
adjustment, a volunteer group of seven
that are appointed by you all, make the
decision on where these locate. In our
central business district, our CBD,
those are actually permitted uses where
they are able to um operate uh lawfully
just by um going through our site plan
and a building uh permit process. Um
what this amendment package does, it
actually touches a number of elements of
our unified development code. Um, number
one, it modifies our non-conforming use
section, our non-conformity section.
What does that do? essentially allows
that if any use that is in our use table
is changed in how it is allowed to
operate. For example, if a permitted use
changes to a conditional use or if a
conditional use changes to a special
use, the city council may include a
separate provision in the ordinance
making that change to say that use has
to cease to exist at a certain date in
the future or seek reapproval. Um the
way that is drafted in this ordinance is
it applies to any future actions. How
does it relate to this specific
ordinance? This specific ordinance has
its own section. It's the very last
section of the ordinance that says that
all existing historic horse racing
activities that are not uh permitted in
their zone district have to go back for
reapproval by the governing body by
December 31st, 2027.
The reason that date was selected and
the reason that provision was put in was
to mirror state statute which recently
adopted uh sunset provisions for the
existing county approved licenses with
the store horse racing. So, the intent
of that is to mirror state statute and
require all of those uses to essentially
come back to the city for approval this
time in front of the governing body
instead of the board of adjustment. Um,
the only one that wouldn't uh require
that approval would be ones that are
located in a new overlay district that
is established and I will get into that
in a little bit more detail.
So, additionally, this ordinance um it
amends our definitions to pull out the
historic horse racing activity from the
um entertainment and recreation other
category and create its own gaming
center definition which includes this
facility, this type of historic horse
racing facility. It amends the special
use approval process which is a
governing body process to approve
special uses. Right now that use is very
limited. That approval process is geared
specifically for oil and gas support
services. We rarely use that process and
it needed a revamp anyway. The last time
it was used was for an oil and gas
exploration facility near the source gas
or near the Black Hills energy power
plant on Industrial Road near HR Ranch.
Um, it also creates a new regional
entertainment overlay district. I'll
touch on where that is. And then it
creates the new development standards uh
related to historic horse racing
facilities that are located outside of
that district.
Um, this is just a quick overview of
what is changing on the nonconforming
section. Um, it's the addition of number
four. This is the one that gives the
governing body the ability to
essentially uh create sunset provisions
or days when uses would not be allowed
to continue if it is in the enacting
ordinance. Um this um may have a couple
of of changes as it moves forward based
on some additional city attorney review.
So we'll be evaluating that between
first public services meeting today and
the next public services meeting.
Uh the next item
is the uh proposed definitions.
Oh, the sorry the next item is a
clarification on how zone district
boundaries are measured. This probably
should have been our development
regulations already, but this basically
indicates if there's ever discrepancy
and interpretation as to where a zone
district starts or it ends or it begins
that the onus lies on the land owner to
provide proof of where that zone
district boundary could be. So in a lot
of cases we have zone districts and and
development standards that are based on
proximity from one thing to the other.
Um it is standard practice and
acceptable within uh professional
planning for the burden of proof to rest
on the land owner to provide any changes
um or to identify if there is an error.
What would this entail? This would
essentially entail a surveyor putting
together um a survey and indicating
where the deficiency lies.
Uh next,
there's a little bit of lag here
is the definition that is being added uh
for the gaming center.
That definition is uh right here. It is
this new uh language that is included in
proposed section. It's in existing
section 1.4.4.c.
Um it is defined as follows. Uh this is
one that is mirrored off of state
statute and also mirrored off of the
activities. With this definition, it
clearly does note that um uses that are
customary with gaming centers can also
be included um in that land use as well.
want to talk a little bit about the
proposed overlay district and I will
pull up a map in just a little bit that
will show you some details on how this
overlay district works. Um, also I will
show you how the development standards
um could be applied to uh different
local and different facilities within um
the scope of this zoning amendment. Um
what we've done is we are modifying the
uh general use table that we have for
our zoning. Um we realized while working
on this that when this was first created
uh there were actually some items that
needed to be included that hadn't been
included in the past. So in addition to
adding the re regional entertainment
overlay district, we recognize some of
the existing ones that exist. One is the
restrictive use control area overlay
district and the other is the urban use
overlay district which is the western
portion of the downtown area. So those
have been included in uh that table. So
they're formerly uh there and recognized
the new regional entertainment overlay
district. Um, it is essentially
describing four different areas which
are to be areas that would be able to
receive a historic horse racing facility
or gaming center as defined. Um, those
areas would simply uh have them as
permitted uses. There would be no
special setback uh standards from um
certain uses, but they would be
essentially incentivized to go to these
areas without having to go through the
special use permit process from the
governing body. These four areas include
the 15th Street area between Capitol and
Reed. That's the area commonly um
discussed as a 15th Street experience.
the Reed rail corridor between 23rd and
the Union Pacific Rail Line with the
caveat that any development that is
occurring um or in that overlay district
has to be adjacent to the Reed Rail
corridor and it also has to have its
primary pedestrian entrance off of the
Reed Rail corridor where it is able to
be done. So, for example, if it is a
public plaza, then it would be required
to take us access off of that. If it
would be an access way or an area where
the public wasn't able to be done, it
would have an exception where it could
go onto an adjacent street.
The West Lincoln corridor, this is West
Lincoln Way corridor. This would be from
Crow Creek all the way to the west to
city limits. Um, this would include
properties within 300 ft of that
corridor on the north and south side of
the roadway. This would include areas
like the hitching post. Um, areas to the
south side of of Lincoln Way between the
railroad tracks. Um, also areas out
towards the west um towards Little
America out that direction including a
portion of Little America land. Um, the
High Plains Road interchange. This is an
area that is measured um alongside
Interstate 80. So it would be um
basically 3,000 feet in either direction
of the interchange to the north and to
the south. And the use would apply to
parcels that are adjacent and only the
first 2500 ft of those parcels. Again, I
will show you a map that describes how
that looks in just a little bit.
Um the development standards uh those
are pretty pretty limited but they do
have an effect on uh some of the
facilities and where they can locate in
the RE regional entertainment overlay
district. The only standard is regarding
facilities that are developed in the
Reed Rail corridor. Essentially what
that says is as noted before it requires
that entrance to be off of the Reed Rail
corridor for pedestrians. um that's
their primary entrance unless it's not
possible.
Uh regarding the other uh locations,
these would be located in the CB and the
CBD zone district. Uh there is a buffer
um proposed that would be 500 ft from
any elementary or secondary school,
child care center,
um uh church, place of worship, or
public park and recreation center.
This is how we presented it to the
planning commission. We had identified
that it only the measurements only
applied to child care centers provided
they were operating in an independent
building alone by themselves. That means
that facility was 100% developed as a
child care center and it isn't just a a
component of an overall multi-unit
building. At the planning commission
meeting that occurred on May 18th, that
provision was modified and it changed it
to all child care centers, even if
they're operating in a multi-tenant
building. Um, on an upcoming page, I'll
show you how that had an effect on some
of our some of our operations.
This is a little detail on the read rail
corridor. That is how that is worded in
the ordinance.
And this is the uh modification that was
made by the planning commission and is
reflected in your ordinance. Um
essentially they removed the wording uh
from a child center to say if any child
care center operates and this is more
than just in a home. This is a child
care center that is um larger and
licensed by the state. if it's anything
um it would require the 500 foot
separation.
Um what that does is that does have a
negative effect on some of our existing
um our existing uh facilities that we
have right now. The way it was initially
drafted um of the seven that we have
within the state limits right now, they
would all remain eligible for reapproval
under the special use approval process.
However, the change to allow for child
care centers um that are in multi-tenant
buildings or associated with another use
does make two facilities um not
eligible. One of those facilities is the
uh derby club on Persing at 1510 East
Persing. That's the one that has the
adjacent bowling alley, all of that that
stuff there. The reason that one would
be ineligible is because Gold's Gym
actually holds a child care center
license and that is a piece of their
development. So that 500 ft radius would
extend into their their facility. Um,
another one that would become um
ineligible would be the Derby Club on
Ridge Road and Persing. That's at 3310
Ridge Road. that one would become not
eligible for special use approval in the
future because next to Papa Murphy's and
the parking lot of the Albertson's
there's a child care center in one of
those uh retail bays.
Um so that's that's what had changed um
with the planning commission
um recommendation on this. Now I'm going
to quickly show you a map real quick.
This map is one that was developed
uh with the spirit of our initial
recommendation to the planning
commission which limited that childc
care buffer to 500 ft for operations in
independent buildings. Um and this is
the site up on Persian
and Concord. Uh this is the derby club.
As you can see, there is a a 500 foot
setback from what's most recently been
from the school the old the former Kerry
Junior High School and now it's
Eastridge
um from that school. That's where your
500 foot um buffer falls.
As we look uh to other areas uh like
along Persing for example,
this here it's a little slow to populate
on the right side of the screen next to
the purple. Um that is the intersection
of Persing and Ridge um near the
Albertson's and the other derby club uh
right where that white uh building is.
The planning commission modification
actually adds
additional radius from there which makes
that use um challenging
at that location.
Um how does this affect other community
business corridors in our community? Um
the orange this is our CB district
that's community business. Um as you can
see these these uh circles these radi
these are areas where it would be
restricted. So, we're seeing the area to
the um this is the Lincoln Way area.
This is Converse in the middle. To the
east and west of Converse, there would
be the ability for uh HHRs and gaming
centers to locate in that area. Um also,
I I'm going to back up for a sec. There
is a provision that in addition to this
buffer from childc carees uh parks um
those types of items that any historic
horse race facility in the CB or the CBD
district um also has to be adjacent to a
collector or minor arterial or principal
arterial street. Those are shown on this
map as either the purple lines, the red
lines, the green lines, and you can
barely see this one, but this is the uh
light brown line. So only uh lands that
are adjacent to those colored streets um
and outside of these radi would be able
to that's where they could locate. So
what you're seeing is you're seeing uh a
lot more limited location. All of these
ones that are um shown outside of those
radi and along those colored street
center lines, those are all ones that
could locate subject to approval by the
governing body.
Um, I would like to note that Depot
Plaza is not considered a park for the
purposes of this. So, that does not
negatively impact any
um of the the locations. It's not
considered a a park per se.
Um, the overlay districts, I'll show you
what those look like real quick.
All right. This here, this is the I'll
start in the downtown area.
This is the area here. This is 15th
Street. So, you'd be looking at the
north half of the block between Lincoln
Way and 15th Street. It's the area
running uh between the depot capital
avenue and the rail spur. So it be these
properties along here for the reed rail.
One of the key components was adjacency.
Um the parcels are different sizes along
the reed rail corridor. So as you can
see this one kind of zigzags in and out.
But these would be areas that would be
eligible. Again, in these areas, that
radius from parks, childc carees, uh
schools, that does not apply in the
overlay district. As you head out
towards uh Lincoln Way,
um this essentially allows the you'll
see as it catches up the land use to
occur within 300 ft of the road right
away. So, it could extend into a portion
of the lot, but there's an absolute
distance that it couldn't be more than
300 ft. The primary purpose for that is
to um keep those in an area where number
one um they're not off the the beaten
path or uh localized in the back area.
They're more brought up front to primary
travel corridors to promote investment
and to have easy access to regional
entertainment options.
Um down south
um this is the area of High Plains Road
interchange and Interstate 25. This is
set up in a way that it extends 3,000 ft
in either direction from the center line
of the roadway where it crosses over. So
that goes to the northeast and to the
southwest. and it requires that um it
would extend to an adjacent property
provided it's number one adjacent and
number two within 2500 ft of the
Interstate 25 rightofway line as
measured perpendicularly. Um in this
particular case it includes a couple of
existing parcels of land north of High
Plains Road. This is an existing
facility right here. There's additional
lands in the north. um and includes
several other areas uh south of High
Plains Road that are adjacent between
Clear Creek Parkway and Interstate 25.
And then for lands that are unplatted
and much larger, um it includes the
adjacent parcel. For example, this is a
parcel that's adjacent on the north side
of Future High Plains Road extension. Um
and then this is the curve of where
those operations would have to stop um
on the south because this area is um not
platted. It's one large tract. For the
purposes of calculating that 2500 ft
distance um specifically excluded
similar to what you see with annexation,
we exclude creeks, rights of way, other
other items like that. excluded are
lands that are operated by a railroad
entity. So that would be the Burlington
Northern track that parallels Interstate
25 and lands that are owned by state or
government agencies. So for example, the
welcome center. So that is excluded.
Um so this uh is a quick overview of of
what is uh going on with this proposed
ordinance. I would like to note that we
are prepared to have a substitute ready
for the next public services meeting
that um will reflect the um original
staff recommendation to planning
commission if that is a direction by the
governing body or this committee um
because it would allow for the continued
operation of existing
um historic horse racing once when the
special use permit
um process occurs. And then sec
secondly, uh we did realize after
discussions with one of the uh local
horse race or one of the local simocass
facilities representatives that we
inadvertently omitted um a zone district
that should um be treated similarly to
the CB community business district. So
we do intend to bring forward um an
amendment through substitution that will
incorporate MUB which is mixeduse
business um in the to treat it the same
as the CB zone district. So that means
it will be modified to include
um the land use in the MUB table for the
for the use table and also in the
development standard section.
I'm I'm open to any questions that you
have regarding this item.
>> Any questions? Uh Dr. Renie,
>> Madam Chairwoman, thank you through you
to Mr. Bloom. So, Mr. Bloom, the
ordinance in front of us today
incorporates the recommendations from
the planning commission.
>> Chair three to members of the committee,
that is correct. Our standard protocol
is to reflect any planning commission
modification
um in the ordinance that's presented to
the to the governing body because we're
presenting their recommendation.
>> I thought our standard was to have those
listed. We would make the motion to
incorporate them if we wanted them. So,
okay, that answered my question.
>> Dr. Thank you, Madam Chairwoman. So, I
just need to get clear on two things. So
this does not
grandfather in for lack of a better word
the existing
uh businesses
should we move forward is that correct
because of the childcare issue
>> chair through you to or chair three to
Dr. Evans, that is correct. The way this
is is set up is it requires any use that
would not be allowed to reapply and then
we would have to uh review them subject
to the development uh standards
including that buffer which would not
give two of the facilities the
protection of at least having the
ability to reapply.
Madam Chairwoman, then I have a a
followup
with the daycare issue.
So I just need to get clear on this
also. So a daycare can be close to
uh an establishment selling alcohol,
but it can't be close to an estab as
close to an establishment doing historic
horse racing. Is that correct,
>> chair? Three to Dr. amendments in the
committee as drafted. Yes, that's
correct.
>> And can you give me the rationale for
that?
>> Chair through you. The goal of this
amendment was strictly to deal with
historic horse racing. It was to draft
amendments regarding store horse racing.
So bars and liquor stores, those items
were not um considered.
>> Well, but why why the concern with the
child care facilities?
chair, members of the committee, Dr.
Emmens. Um the reason we we put those
those spaces in were number one, we were
asked to consider um the spacing
requirements and then we modeled those
after our sexually oriented businesses
where there are setbacks that are
commonly enforced through local zoning
codes for um different types of
businesses and establishments from
churches, from childcare centers, uh
schools, parks and recreation
facilities. And that's that's where we
went with that as we followed that.
>> Um, Madam Chair, so I guess and and I
just want to be on the record that I
spent a large number of years advocating
for child care and children's issues.
So, I'm not trying to throw kids under
the bus or anything, but I'm just trying
to figure out
the connection, I guess, is is eluding
me as to it's it's not considered an
adult entertainment, I wouldn't think. I
mean, yes, adults go there, but adults
go lots of places that's close to child
care. So I'm just trying to align the
connection between the two.
>> Yeah. Chair, members of the of the
committee. Um yes, it really is a a
preference of the governing body if they
wish to have that separation included or
not included. Um it's not uncommon for
childc carees to have uh separation or
create separation requirements for
specific land uses. At this time, the
focus was primarily on the historic
horse racing. Um, we did um note that as
this went through, it would it would
seem that it would be fair to apply it
to um the bars and liquor stores.
However, it was outside the scope of the
amendment we were drafting.
>> Any other questions for staff?
Okay. Any public comment?
Good afternoon.
>> Good afternoon. Tracy Lake. I serve as
general counsel to Wyoming Downs and 307
Horse Racing. Uh thank you for having me
today. Uh we support the zoning change
overall. Um we respectfully request that
this committee um consider reverting
back to um how the planning commission
staff presented of the buffer for child
care centers. Um and that is that you
know it's a child care center that's um
own independent buildings um and it's
their sole use.
Uh you know the change that the planning
commission made actually um would make
two of our facilities out of compliance.
That is our Persian location and our
Ridge Road location. A couple of things
to note. Um both our facilities went
through the conditional use process um
that's currently in place and uh was
approved and the city has already
considered the location of these
existing uh businesses and them to
operate. Uh the investment in these
facilities is significant. Um the
Persian facility we've invested about
$20 million um to make that facility
what it is. It's pretty impressive. and
the Ridge Road location. We just spent a
little over $4 million. Uh to date,
these locations have generated a little
over $4 million in tax revenue for the
city of Cheyenne.
Um as you I'm sure are all aware, the
Persing location has a successful
bowling alley, an arcade, um it has a
children's play center, uh laser tag,
escape rooms. Um and these are for all
ages. Of course, our OTB is um our Simoc
casting facility is completely
separated. Only 21 and older is allowed
in that and we do monitor it very
closely. U we've had no issues um with
that and and without that Simocast
facility, those other amenities would
not be able to be present.
Um all of our OTBs in the state are 21
and over. Uh it's actually the law that
it's 18 and up, but we have self-
selected to make our facilities 21 and
up. And that's because we do serve
alcohol. So if you're under 21, you
can't be in our facilities. Um
additionally, we've worked really hard
to have a good working relationship with
the Cheyenne Police Department. Um we
help them whenever they have requests
and we and we really have had fairly
insignificant issues at both of those
locations.
I I did think it's important to note um
the Ridge location of course operated as
a bar uh for many many years um and then
we took it over and additionally the
office bar and grill um which has a
smoking lounge and cigar lounge in the
back there um operates even closer to
that child care center. Uh that's an
issue in Gold's Gym.
Uh with these comments again, we
respectfully request that this um this
committee consider substituting back um
into the 500 foot buffer uh for childc
care facilities. We are okay with that
buffer. Um and I also do just want to
thank the uh city staff. They are always
so helpful and they take our calls and
they listen and we just really
appreciate them so much. I'm happy to
stand for any questions. Thank you.
>> Uh Mark Moody, Shine City Council Ward
3. Um as a sponsor of it, I would like
to see the remove what the plan
commissioner recommended revert back to
what was originally sponsored. I don't
know how my colleagues feel they're also
sponsors, but again, I think as was said
before, I think the 500 is more than
acceptable. So, I'll stand for
questions.
>> Yes, Dr. U. Madam Chair, and I don't
know if I don't know who to ask this
question to. Um, with there being a
children's play center in the facility
on Ridge, does that in itself not
the place cause some kind of significant
issues?
Chair three to members of the committee.
Charles Bloomplay the Bman director that
is not a licensed child care center
within their building. So it it would
not cause any issues.
>> So So um Madam Chair, so we're just
concerned if they're licensed
>> chair through you. That is correct.
>> Okay. Just that seems
>> Yeah. Okay.
Any other public comment?
>> Madame Chair, members of the committee,
um fellow councilmen, my name is Larry
Wolf. I'm city council representative uh
from Ward One. um just sitting here
listening to this and I'm not a sponsor
of this and I haven't heard really
anything about this other than a brief
conversation with Dr. Renie. Um strikes
me that this is a very important and
complicated issue um that is uh first of
all you're going to have to educate some
other people on the council about it, me
included. Uh and so I wonder whether I
mean this ought to be maybe a subject of
a work session or something that in fact
is presented to really educate us. We've
heard from Miss Leot. I mean, do you
represent all of the HR the
who are the other operators?
>> Okay. And have they been involved in
this process?
>> Just as a note, you need to
>> No, Madam Chairman, I mean, just have
these other companies been involved in
this process?
>> And that would be a question that
perhaps Mr. Bloom could answer.
through the members of the committee.
Um, Bal presently isn't operating a
facility here right now. We just were
alerted that they did file a conditional
use application, I believe, over the
weekend. So, they will be making a entry
into the market and we have not received
any comments from the other operator.
>> Mr. Mr. Bloom, do you know if they've
been notified of this proposed change?
>> Chair, members of the committee, I'm not
a we did not do direct notification to
these individuals. Um, we do we did not
do direct notification.
>> Thank you,
>> Madam Chair. um through you just um I
guess my point is that we're going to
need to hear a lot about this these uh
designations of these uh restricted
areas. That alone has obviously
consequences for these companies and
maybe other conse other companies. We've
heard no discussion about that at all.
Now maybe we can deal with this as this
makes its way through the full council,
but there might be other ways to better
educate us and to allow the community to
have uh some input into these um really
significant decisions. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Any other public comments?
Okay.
>> Hearing seeing no other public comment,
um I would entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I move to approve on
second reading.
Madame Chair, I second. So we we have a
motion by Dr. Renie and a second by Dr.
Emmans. Is there any discussion?
>> Madam Chairwoman?
>> Yes, Dr. Renie. it. Um
since there will be amendment coming to
us for um
either Monday night or the next public
service committee meeting to remove the
language from
that was proposed by the
um planning commission. I will probably
want to make introduc introduce that
amendment at that time just so people
know. But I want to go through a little
bit through the history of this. Um,
when I first and first of all, I guess I
want to thank our planning office. They
have put, as you can tell, I mean, we
rarely have a staff report that's as
long as this was. And they have put a
tremendous amount of work into this. Um,
and I think actually they've come up
with a pretty good product. It's pretty
much what if you remember I talked to
many of you about this um months ago and
the rationale was that at the time there
were seven historic course racing venues
in in um Laram County or no pardon me in
Cheyenne. There were nine in the county.
There were seven in Cheyenne. Six of
those only one of those was zoned
properly and the other six had gone
through our processes
and had received a conditional use
permit from the board of adjustments
which is as we all know is an appointed
board. they're not elected like we are.
And um and at the time when some of the
more recent HHR establishments were
being developed, all of us I think
received significant number of emails
asking why
um why we were allowing all these. Well,
for two reasons. One, at the time, state
statute did not give us control over
where those went. Senate File 45 this
year that was approved during the budget
session does allow municipalities to
have some input into the decision. But
the other thing is with it going through
the board of adjustments
um it never did come to us.
So the rationale for for the ordinance
was that
first of all we would allow um
allow in in the overlay areas
um that they go ahead and be approved
under the normal approval process. And
those four areas were picked as areas
that we wanted to perhaps stimulate or
encourage some development in. And Mr.
Bloom has talked about those four areas
being 15th Street, Reed Avenue, um,
West Lincoln Way, and the area out.
Obviously, we had to include the area by
out by the interchange because we
already had development there. So, we
picked those areas as areas that would
maybe be a little easier to develop an
HHR facility because it wouldn't have to
go through the council. And any place
outside of those four areas would have
to actually if they want, we're not
saying they could not do that, but if
they want to develop somewhere outside
of those four designated areas, they
would actually have to now get a special
use permit, which means it'd have to be
approved by the governing body, which
made more sense because we're the
elected representatives.
Um,
couple other parts of this is that
they
are going to be handled just like like
liquor permit permits. They will be
reviewed periodically. That review is
based on the state gaming commission
allows them to their approvals to last
up to three years. And so our ordinance
kind of mirrors that as well. So that's
the rationale behind the ordinance. It
does bring the control a little more to
the city. It does encourage development
in some areas where we'd like to see
development. Um I do think it, you know,
as far as the
500 ft, you know, to my colleague from
War 2's questions, if she wants to amend
that, we can consider it. And I do think
we should do go back to the original
form and not incorporate the planning
commission's recommendations. So, um, I
would hope that we would all consider
voting in approval. Thank you, Madam
Chairwoman.
>> Thank you, Dr. Winnie. Dr. Evans.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairwoman. Um, I'm
going to vote for this and I, uh, but I
want to revisit the child care issue.
So, I'm not prepared to do that today,
but I do want to bring that back, at
least give it some more attention and
make sure that either we are giving them
500 ft or we're figuring out what to do
about those people who are already in
play. So, that's
Thank you. Hey, so we have a motion and
a second. Any other discussion from the
dis
hearing? None. Um all in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed. This item will move forward
with recommendation uh to approve at the
next council meeting.
>> Number 18, ordinance, second reading,
amending chapter 15.20 National
Electrical Code adopted. Appendix K,
International Building Code,
administrative provisions adopted of
title 15, buildings and construction of
the municipal code of the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming, updating the
incorporated national electrical code
provisions as specified.
>> Okay. Can we have a staff report,
please?
Madam Chair, members of the council,
Anthony Parmlo, chief building official,
city of Cheyenne. Um, what we have
before us is the adoption of the
National Electrical Code. It is, uh, a
document that is updated every 3 years.
Um, it is in force by the state of
Wyoming and we are required as a
jurisdiction, all jurisdictions across
the state are required to follow suit um
within 180 days of the state's adoption.
State has adopted it. Its date is
January 1st of 2026
and that is the ordinance that's before
you. I would want to make mention that
staff has evaluated
um the code itself the changes costwise
are minimal to uh residential
structures. There are some cost that do
come up for commercial but they are more
from a safety standpoint. Um if I may to
give you an example one is of doors on
equipment that would open up and paths
of egress. We don't want those blocked.
So those are kind of what we're seeing.
The majority of what is also contained
within the document that has changed is
mostly housekeeping. Uh moving sections
from one part of the code to another
part of the code that makes more
logistical sense as well as just basic
housekeeping. Um staff has conducted a
open house meeting that we had on the
28th here in council chambers last
Thursday. We had one individual attend.
His name was Dick Mason. He is actually
the prior plans examiner for the city of
Cheyenne. Served many years on staff. Um
question that he had was just about two
documents, one being the electrical code
and one being the IRC. Um we seem to
work through those. There were not many
other comments beyond that and to my
knowledge the clerk has not received any
comments from public as well. I would
stand for any questions that you might
have.
>> Thank you. Are there any questions for
Mr. Pommel?
M Dr. Renie? No, ma'am.
>> Okay, thank you. Um, any public comment?
>> Okay, I would entertain a motion.
>> Move to approve on second.
>> I'll second. We have a motion from Dr.
Renie and a second from Dr. Emmens to
approve on second reading. Um, any
discussion on the dis
hearing? None. All in favor say I. I
>> I
>> opposed. This item will move forward
with recommendation to approve at the
next meeting of the council.
>> Next item, please. Number 26, resolution
authorizing the mayor to execute limited
site access and due diligence agreements
for city-owned property commonly known
as the Belgore Ranch.
>> Staff report.
>> Madame Chairman, members of the
committee, for the record, I'm Mayor
Patrick Collins. So for the last five or
six years now, we've been working on
trying to uh maybe develop part of the
Bellevore Ranch, specifically the uh
eastern part of the ranch. Um Mr. Crave
has been working very hard on this and
uh we have now a couple companies who
are interested in looking at doing some
development there and as part of that
they want to be able to get onto the
ranch to do some due diligence, look at
environmental things, um you know the
quality of the ground that they would be
attaching their facilities to that type
of thing. And so what this resolution
does is gives my office the ability to
enter into access agreement agreements
with entities looking to develop on the
Belvore Ranch. Um
this is not the agreement itself. It's
just the authority to do that. Um our
council person from Ward One sent a very
good uh email earlier. I maybe it was
last evening about uh this agreement and
most of the things that are in his email
have been addressed like data sharing.
Anybody that goes on to the ranch we we
have included in our um our process uh
that they must share the data with us.
um that there's timelines. It's not an
open-ended um
uh not an open-ended agreement where
they can be on there forever. Um it does
limit the scope of what they can do uh
while they're on the ranch. Uh mostly
survey, environmental, and they need to
drill uh some holes to find out what the
soils are like. Uh do some LAR testing
um so they know exactly what the
topography is like. Um it does not
include the uh financial requirements.
We've we've actually went out and
recruited these companies, sent them
letters asking them to come. We' felt
like uncomfortable asking them to pay
then to uh go on the ranch that we asked
them to come and develop on. Um and it's
this agreement is not the actual
agreement that would cause us in the
future to uh approve those. Any approval
of a development in the future would
have to come back to the governing body.
All this does is gives them the ability
to go on the ranch, do their due
diligence to make sure it's suitable for
development. Are there Indian tepee
rings and things like that that might be
in the way um that would cause it or uh
um
animals or ve or vegetation that uh is
critical that you know you couldn't be
able to develop wetlands, those types of
things. And so that's what's uh what's
before you today. And uh if we can get
this approval, we do have a couple of
companies that are interested in going
out doing that kind of work and uh we
would hope that maybe something good
would come out of that. Are there any
questions for the mayor?
>> Okay, thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Any public comment?
Hello, uh, council men and women. I am
Will Robinson. I'm the Bellevar Ranch
Manager. Um,
I would strongly encourage you to pass
this today because these environmental
studies will not only benefit the
environment out there, but the ranch
itself and the development. Um, some of
the areas that we're looking at do have
raptors um, present right now are
elkurds down there and they're cving.
So, we want to make sure that we're not
affecting that along with this
development. I understand that progress
is going to happen. development is going
to happen, but I want to make sure that
we do it the right way. So, I I hope
that we can approve this and move
forward. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Any other public comment?
>> Madam Chairman, members of the council,
my name is Larry Wolf, city council
representative one. Um, you do have an
email from me uh on this uh subject and
I certainly support us doing this.
But I I think there's some omissions
from this document that uh the the
committee and the council are going to
need to address. First of all, um
let's talk a little history here. Um the
you have a master plan for the Belvore
Ranch and then you had an updated master
plan for the Belvore Ranch. Um that
master plan um made a strong
recommendation that the city itself
conduct studies on the Belvore Ranch to
identify sites to do the kinds of
environmental studies that um uh the
ranch manager just talked about. Um the
city's done nothing with that. So um and
over many years now there have been
discussions about with these other
companies Um, but
we should be thinking like a land owner.
We shouldn't just be thinking that uh uh
this is something that we want to entice
people on. Uh these kinds of agreements,
trespass agreements, land access
agreements are common all over this
state and uh uh and but they are very
carefully drafted and um they're
designed to both protect the land owner,
us, and to allow these studies to go
forward. And all these land owners are
in the same position we are. They
generally want the development because
they want the royalties from the oil and
gas companies or the big companies, but
um they also want their land protected.
Um so I made some suggestions just
reading through it that aren't addressed
here. The first one is that there's that
says nothing about who owns this data.
That is absolutely in all these
agreements one of the critical aspects
to it. Uh, and in general, the land
owner either wants to own the data
that's generated on their land or they
want to make sure they have an absolute
right to obtain copies of everything.
And this is maps, surveys, you name it,
geotechnical information.
This doesn't authorize or direct at all
that that issue. And I think you
definitely need to uh address that or
we'll address it when this comes before
the full council. Um second of all,
most land owners charge people coming on
their property for the right to do that
and the right to gather information.
Uh now that's a judgment that that the
city can make and the the governing body
can make too. But uh if you think you
might want to do that because once once
we start allowing this, you don't know
who's going to come on. And there may be
some solar companies we'd like to entice
on or a natural gas company, but it
could be a whole bunch of different
people, some of whom we may want, some
of whom we may not, or some of whom we
say, "Okay, you can come on our
property, but here's what it's going to
cost you." So we ought to at least
consider and the body governing body
ought to at least consider uh should we
allow a mechanism to charge for this and
there are any number of ways to levy
those costs you can do it on a per day
basis you can do it you know how many
miles of surveying they want to do uh
etc but it would seem to me if you're
going to pass an ordinance like this if
we're going to pass an ordinance like
this we need to at least address that
issue um And there are other issues. How
much geotech work are we gonna allow?
Are they going to be allowed to drill uh
sort of wherever they want? Um are we
going to set limitations on that? Are
they going to be able to drill a water
monitoring well? Are they going to be
allowed to put a uh weather station
there? Because uh a lot of companies uh
who have solar projects want to be able
to uh establish stations that gather
data for considerable amount of time. uh
weather stations the same way air
quality monitoring. So there are a
number of considerations here and while
yes we can leave we the council can
leave those to the general discretion of
the mayor who we obviously trust and
then the city attorney. um we at least
ought to be able to to give to the
mayor's office some real specific
authorities on data on charging on how
long we expect uh these companies to uh
be able to operate. So I um I mean we
can
up to you madam chairman and members of
the committee. Uh you could address
those things right now. We could uh
draft some amendments for consideration
by the council when it comes to us. Um
but I would uh encourage you that these
are not issues that we want to not have
addressed in here. And when the ranch
manager says, "Well, we'd love to have
information on wildlife, environmental
consideration, cultural resources,"
there's absolutely no certainty that
we're going to get any of that from
these companies. Um, I mean, they may
come in and say, "We wanted to look at
just this specific land, and we'll know
nothing about any of the rest of the
ranch." uh or they may do, you know,
cultural resources assessment or an
endangered species assessment on only
part of it. So there's there are bigger
issues here that reflect on what the the
land owners, the city really wants out
of this property. and they're clearly
implicated in the work and that we've
already paid for for uh the um uh
updated uh master plan. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
And I may have misunderstood, but I
thought I understood the mayor may merit
to say that um those ideas that you had
shared in the email were being
integrated into thisou.
Um, so will we see a corrected copy of
that
or substitution perhaps at the next
or the actual MOU? I'm guessing we'll
see as it's finalized.
>> Madam Chairman, to answer your specific
question, where Patrick Collins, um,
what this resolution does is gives us
the authority to enter into individual
agreements with companies that want to
come on and in those individual
agreements, we will handle all of those
situations. Um
I know for a fact right now the data is
already in the ones that we're working
on. Um we're not we don't have an
intention to charge because again we
invited the people um limitations of
what geotechnical work they can do. Um
you know the timelines those things have
all been addressed.
>> Will those mayor come back before the
council individually asus?
Was that your intention?
>> I don't think so.
>> No that was not your intention.
No, I I think that was the reason that
we have this resolution before you today
is so we didn't have to do that so we
can react when those those questions
come. Um, but we will and and we have
already done most of those things and uh
we'll look at and see if there's
anything that's missing uh on this list
from the one we're working on currently.
We have one company we're currently
working on an access agreement with.
We'll make sure that it includes all of
these things.
>> Thank you,
>> Madam Chairman. through you to the
mayor.
>> Mayor Collins,
>> you needed some steps today. Correct.
>> Thinking that same thing, sir.
>> Um
and perhaps by Monday, our colleague
will be a little more satisfied with But
if we were to postpone for two weeks, is
that would that be harmful at all?
chairman through you Amber Ash chief of
staff. Um I would need to reach out to
speak with the company that we are
currently in negotiations with um on the
access agreement. We had um let them
know that we were putting forth this
resolution and had set um the timeline
based on that. So, I will need to seek
additional clarification on what a
two-eek delay might mean for them and
their planning purposes.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Chairman,
>> any other questions
from the committee?
>> Yes, Councilman Labour.
Madame Chairman, uh,
Madame Chairman, I, uh, have kind of an
unusual question here, uh, but I think
it has direct relevancy to what we're
discussing, and that is the, uh, email
that, uh, Councilman Wolf prepared. And,
uh, my question is, Madam Chairman, can,
uh, that email be entered into the
record of this meeting today?
it. I'm sure it could be. Uh would you
like to introduce that to be introduced
into the record?
>> Yes, I'd like to uh make sure that
everyone on the council and certainly
has that opportunity over the next
period of time to really um understand
what the concerns that were raised here.
And uh I I fully I want to preface this
a little bit uh Madame Chairman with my
deep desire to see this project and the
use of the Belvore Ranch continue. It
has really uh proven itself over time
with the windmills. I look forward to uh
the opening of the uh uh trail system
and uh I know that the water development
is still um a possibility that probably
becomes more important as we look at uh
water shortages and the issues we might
have in the not too distant future. So,
it's a complex matter and it is one that
uh we really want to be sure that we are
uh doing the very things that are
suggested here in this in this email. I
am certainly not an expert in this
matter, but I'd like to learn more. Um,
and I think that would be an opportunity
for us to do that if we postponed it
Monday or made some sort of action here
that would um really uh give us a chance
to really look delve into exactly what's
conceived of. I mean, is this uh just a
uh solar field? Does it have some other
considerations here that might be
studied? Um, I'd like to know. And I
know that all of this occurs in an area
where there are other uses uh and how
they all fit together. So, um
uh do you need a motion here uh Madame
Chairman or or are you ordering
directing this to be in the record?
Well, let the record reflect that the
email dated May 31st, I believe it is,
from uh Councilman Wolf as um generated
by Gemini AI from his prompt will be um
added to the uh record for today's
meeting.
>> So, may I continue?
>> Sure.
it. I think I've covered most of it
here, but I think this is something that
definitely has some relevance in terms
of the other
activities that are going on and are
conceived of in the not too uh distant
neighborhood. This is uh um how close uh
the the far end of the eastern portion
of the Bilvore intersects with uh what
might happen uh with a number of
projects and certainly it is really
about uh that that use of that energy is
uh my assumption is that that there is a
great need for energy and if if the city
of Cheyenne can benefit financially from
that as we did with the with the
windmills. I think that's a very good
thing. So, I hope that we can uh really
flesh this out because um I'd like to
know who
in who are we in discussions with, what
what's their background? Um and and
again, um there's a deep desire on my
part to see uh u that use. It certainly
is. Uh been a long time since we bought
the Bellevore. Uh a number of those
things have come to pass. A number of
them haven't. So, um I think we'll look
at that and see. And I appreciate uh
Councilman Wolf's uh input. I think
those are that's that's a valuable part
of our discussion and I look forward to
uh following up on this. And I'm not
sure who I should contact, Madame
Chairman, but I'd sure like to look at
the uh originating documents of the uh
planning and design of the windmills. I
think there's some similarity there that
I'd be interested in. And so
I'm not sure who the what historical uh
department would would be there, but and
and I and I also want to express my
concern. We did the we did the adoption
of the master plan. We we changed that.
We looked at uh basically something
similar to this uh as a city project.
and now we're looking to what I assume
to be a private uh consulting firm or
entity. So, questions that need to be
answered and I appreciate uh your uh
taking a look at this unusual procedure
that I suggested. Thank you, Madam
Chairman.
>> Thank you, Councilman Laybourne. Um and
I would direct you to uh Mr. Bloom in
the planning office and also public
works may have some of those original
documents from when the wind energy was
developed on the Bellevore um in their
offices and they're shaking their heads
but um they can put you in touch with
someone. So um any other comments from
the dis? We have a motion and a second.
All in favor say I.
>> We don't have a motion.
>> I'm sorry I thought you made the motion.
Okay. I would entertain a motion.
>> Chairwoman, I'll move to adopt.
>> I'll second. We have a motion from Dr.
Renie and a second from Dr. Emmens. Um,
is there any further discussion?
>> All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed?
>> We've concluded our business on the
agenda for today. The meeting is
adjourned.